The challenge with incomplete
requirements going into a model when
it's building a software system is that
ambiguity at a minimum becomes some sort
of hallucinated feature that the model
has made up and potentially becomes
masses of rework and wasted tokens and
ultimately real kind of code smell in
the repository as well. So the ultimate
artifacts winds up harmed as well. And
so I think of it as as almost like
context engineering on steroids for
software projects and making sure that
the model is as well as possible
grounded in the what that it's building.
Be able to give that steer not in a
one-shot prompt, but in some
documentation. That's where I see spec
driven and BMA being really really
strong. What does BMA mean to you? Build
more architect dream. It's this really
interesting open-source project. What
it's about is giving a model the best
context possible to go and autonomously
build software.
>> [music]
>> Before we jump into this episode, I
wanted to let you know that this podcast
is for developers building with AI at
the core. So whether that's exploring
the latest tools, the workflows, or the
best practices, this podcast is for you.
And really quick ask, 90% of people who
are listening to this haven't yet
subscribed. So if this content has
helped you build smarter, hit that
subscribe button and maybe a like. All
right, back to the episode.
Hello and welcome to another episode of
the AI Native Dev. My name is Simon
Maple and I'm your host uh for this this
episode and uh today we're going to have
a really fun chat about something called
BMA and the BMA method. Um so this is I
I believe it's called a Build More
Architect Dream, which is a which is a
fun way of of really talking about a
spec driven approach to to to building
software um where we really think about
specifications first and then drive the
code uh from there. It allows us to
really think about how we create uh our
intent versus thinking about the how too
early. We capture those behaviors and
those constraints uh very very early in
the process. And taking us through this
is uh Kean Clark uh from Nearform. And
Kean and I have done a a couple of
things including actually uh we we we we
shared the stage at AI Native Dev uh oh
sorry, AI Native Dev Con in New York in
May and we also uh we also did a a
meetup very recently as well in London.
Um Kean, welcome to the podcast. How are
you? Yeah, thanks so much for having me.
I'm doing well. Brilliant brilliant. And
so you're ahead of AI at at Nearform,
right? Tell us a little bit about what
that entails.
Yeah, absolutely. So it's really about
realizing customers' ambitions in the
world of AI. Uh and more recently of
course lots of generative AI. That's
been something that's been keeping us
pretty busy. Um and so that might look
like, you know, unearthing a bunch of
proprietary knowledge that some customer
might have in their product to their end
customers. It might be, you know,
building some sort of agentic system to
make their teams go faster.
Um
but of late we've also been thinking an
awful lot not just about what we build
in the space of AI, but also how we
build it. Yeah. Um and so Nearform sort
of came of age in the era of Node.js and
that's been sort of the technology we've
been known for. Um and actually we've
been thinking a lot lately about AI
native delivery and and delivering with
AI models and the enhanced capabilities
of coding models and spec driven.
And so that's really brought our paths
together, I suppose.
Um since we are very interested in all
of the tool sets and and ways to to to
build software artifacts through AI. So,
you know, more about the how we build as
well as what we build with AI. Which is
super interesting cuz like, you know,
there's a lot of obviously kind of like
you you know, consultancies and people
like that who who are really not
adopting AI in a very interesting way,
but you're really kind of like leading a
lot of the way with with a very you
know, spec oriented and and and future
thinking path of building with AI. So
we'll explore some of this
um
in just a second. Let What do we first
talk a little bit about about BMA? What
What What's What does BMA mean to you?
Yeah, absolutely. So to me it's sort of
the best approximation we have right now
of what a comprehensive spec driven
workflow looks like.
Um
and so it it's, you know, the the
there's a a sort of a tagline attached
to BMA of Build More Architect Dream,
but it's also sort of named by the the
guy who created it, Brian Madsen. So
BMA.
Um
and it's it's this really interesting
open-source project, which I think is
quite important to us at Nearform since
a lot of our pedigree comes from the
world of open source and and
contributing upstream to things like
Fastify and Node core.
Um and so yeah, the fact that this is an
open-source framework that is also open
to the selection of model vendor and
open to the selection of IDE tool set as
well is something that really really
appealed to us. Um and in my head
actually at its very core what it's
about is just like really intelligent
context engineering with a model.
Um and that's kind of what spec driven
is all about.
Um at least in my head, you know, giving
a model the best context possible to go
and autonomously build software. Right.
And it as I say, best approximation I've
seen to date of how to go about doing
that. And I didn't know that about the
name, the BMA. That's That's Brian
Madison, is it? That's it. Yeah. Mad
Madison Madson. I think it's Madison.
>> Madison, sorry. Madison. So so it so so
it started as a name and it was
searching for an acronym. That's what
That That really I think so. Yeah,
exactly. The acronym now is uh is a bit
of a stretch, I feel. But Now the Build
More Architect Dream makes a ton more
sense. I was looking at it and thinking,
"Wow, where where where did this come
from?" But now it all makes a lot more
sense. But it's it's a catchy name,
yeah. Um and it started with this
person, but you know, there's a huge
suite of contributors now on this this
tool set. And it's this really vibrant
open-source project that's gone through
a couple of different versions. Um it's
got a really cool the V6 version that's
just released has a bunch of really nice
developments in terms of uh being able
to select the like the scale of project
you're working on. It's got a module
system where you can bring your own
roles. So it's it's really evolved
massively over the last kind of couple
of months. Yeah, yeah. Let's Let's get
into that a little bit. But I guess the
one question that I'd love to ask cuz I
know Nearform, you know, do a lot of
work in kind of like the the discovery
of various, you know, a lot of the
research and discovery of various tools.
I know you're you're big fans of Keiro,
for example. I know we've talked in the
past about about using Tessell for, you
know, discovering context and learning
about, you know, how agents can be you
know, much better enabled. Um where did
you Where did you first learn about
Where did you How did you kind of like
go through the discovery period with
with BMA?
Yeah, so it sort of came out of our own
internal discovery process really.
Um and we would do very frequently in
consulting this kind of discovery
process that we call ignite, which is
about aligning a bunch of stakeholders
on what it that exactly it is that they
want to build.
Um
and you know, in in the world of
consulting we call this discovery, but
like it happens in every company.
Basically a bunch of folk getting
together and um talking about what the
requirements are for the thing they're
looking to build. What's really
important, like what levers within the
business is it going to impact. Um and
being able to document some of that
stuff, you know, really really well. And
we noticed that we could use things like
AI note takers within the meeting to be
able to capture a lot of that context
and then distill it down into playback
decks and also distill it down into
requirements documents.
Um and so it was the folk who were
facilitating these sessions um that
observed that actually you can get
really good requirements documentation
and backlogs off the back of these
meetings just talking about how and what
it is exactly that we want to build. And
I know the folks in AWS do this a lot
with their pre-read time in meetings
when they're doing their PRFAQ's.
And now they've moved to this term
called squad mobbing. So this is, you
know, really big, you know, methodology
in industry as well. This idea of
gathering requirements
um as a group and then using that as an
artifact to then later go and build.
And so we kind of spotted, you know, we
had been vibe coding prototypes that we
would later throw away and because
that's what you tend to do with an
artifact that's vibe coded. But actually
like could we ground the the the process
of using AI to develop with these
artifacts?
>> [snorts]
>> And that kind of aha moment happened
probably about 6 months ago and it
wasn't me who had it. It's It's a member
of my team, James, who who helped helped
out there and discovered this tool
called BMA along the way that is really
really good at taking some of that
documentation and using it to hone the
output of a model. Um
and so I discovered this spec driven
thing and as a pretty like skeptic, you
know, vibe coding skeptic, that this was
sort of a revelation for me because all
of a sudden you were actually able to
steer what the model did. And yeah, that
was that was pretty powerful, I think.
Yeah, and a lot of the things that
you're kind of like talking about here,
whether it's spec driven or BMA, they're
they're really they're really kind of
like smart and and I guess, you know,
they're solutions that are well thought
out. But I guess
when we when we go back to the root
problem, what what would you say is the
What would you say is the need for these
for these types of solutions?
Yeah, for for me it it came down to like
forcing the the world of vibe coding to
sort of grow up a little bit and have
some guardrails. Uh and so distilling
that
um you know, uncertainty with what the
where the model would would would fill
in the gap, instead have stakeholders
fill in the gap and make sure the
requirements were actually complete.
Um because the the the challenge with
incomplete requirements going into a
model when it's building a software
system is that ambiguity at a minimum
becomes some sort of, you know,
hallucinated feature that the model has
made up. Uh and potentially becomes
masses of rework and wasted tokens
and ultimately, you know, real kind of
code smell in the repository as well. So
the ultimate artifacts winds up kind of
harmed as well. And so I kind of think
of it as as, you know, almost like
context engineering on steroids for
software projects and making sure that
the model is as well as possible
grounded in the what that it's building
as well as the how you want it to build.
Being able to give that steer, not in a
one-shot prompt, but in some
documentation. That that's kind of where
I see spec-driven and and BEMAD being
really really strong. And what's really
interesting here is kind of like when we
think about what, you know, the way
[clears throat] BEMAD goes around trying
to solve this. And so and specs, you
know, if we if we think back well part
well before kind of the AI boom here,
you know, we were doing the we were
thinking about these types of these
types of things back in the BDD days and
things like that. And it's interesting
that when we talk about the problem now,
the problem is is is very, you know,
the problem definition is peppered with
AI terms. And and I think like now the
problem is actually far greater because
of those types of things. So a lot of
things that you say about, you know, the
issues around vibe coding, those types
of things, they magnify the problem
which, you know, like you say, vague
requirements and things like that that
we previously had. It's just magnified
so much more because of the additional
complexity that that that that that vibe
coding and these types of agents can
bring along as well. Yeah, like as
engineers, if we had a gap in
requirements documentation that seemed
really obvious that would impact users,
you know, we would go and ask a
clarifying question of a product manager
of somebody who's a stakeholder on the
project. And we'd be a little annoyed by
it. Like, come on, we're mid-sprint, why
didn't you think of this? But we'd fill
in that gap. The model just makes
up, right? That's that's not a great
outcome. Yeah. Yeah. Yeah. Sometimes it
is, but sometimes a lot of the time it
isn't. Yeah. Yeah. Um so so let let
let's go ahead and and kind of like talk
take us through an example kind of like
NearForm rollout, I guess, of a BEMAD
project, I guess. I guess there are
certain times when it's worked better
and certain times when maybe you've
actually learned actually, you know,
it's not quite as good here. Talk us
through, you know, one of the one of the
most solid kind of BEMAD rollouts that
that you guys have done.
Yeah, [clears throat] so it's it's sort
of to date become the tool of choice for
dev teams at NearForm who are looking to
progress things in an AI-native manner.
Probably alongside Kiro as the other
strong contender.
And all along, the observation I had had
was that it is not a great tool for
actually kind of rapid prototyping and
building, you know, a functional
prototype that you plan to throw away at
the end
because the process is quite heavy.
It has actually made great leaps and
bounds in V6's release in terms of
enabling you to say the sort of level of
project that you're looking to build.
And if you're looking to build a
prototype, it simplifies the workflow.
Haven't had enough hands-on time with it
to to form an opinion but traditionally
rapid prototyping still reaching for
bold.new or something. But where we're
looking to actually build some sort of
MVP and something that's actually
shippable in the greenfield, we found it
absolutely fantastic.
>> [cough]
[clears throat]
>> I think there are probably some
challenges to date in the brownfield,
although it is the best thing I've come
across for working in large brownfield
codebases. Nonetheless,
you know, there there are challenges
with that.
But for greenfield projects, it's been
fantastic.
And the way I kind of try to approach
this, so my my background is not in
consulting. I'm relatively new to the
world of consulting. I've mostly worked
in product companies through engineering
leadership roles. And I like to think
about, you know, rolling out these tool
sets to teams of developers through the
context of like developer empathy.
So we talk a lot about customer empathy
in the sales process, but I think
developer empathy is actually a very
important thing to recognize as an
engineering leader. And it's like this,
when you were, you know, when you were
hands-on keyboard walking in the shoes
of a developer, what stuff did you just
hate? Like, what drove you mad? And so
like, you know, writing infrastructure
as code stacks only to have the the
CloudFormation deploy roll back 15 times
in a row and having to go back and
delete stuff manually and just that that
drudgery I used hate. Or, you know,
fixing an automation test that's that's
blown up because a pixel moved 10 pixels
to the button moved 10 pixels to the
right in the middle of the night. Like,
that's really frustrating, not a good
use of my time.
Even documentation. So all of those
tasks, you know, how can we introduce
tooling into the AI development life
cycle AI into the development life cycle
to make those things
a lot less painful.
So like, what would developers really
gravitate towards,
you know, in trying to automate away
some of that pain? And to that end, you
know, something that I wonder is like,
do developers actually really enjoy
writing documentation and specs, right?
Cuz this whole methodology is based on
spending a lot of time with a markdown
file.
And I think some do, some don't.
But but as I think about how to roll
out, you know, both BEMAD and a broader
suite of sort of MCP-enabled tools that
are that are connected into an IDE, I
like to think about the sort of
developer archetypes that are going to
be interacting with these systems and
what are they actually getting from it?
What makes their life like that bit
easier? Super interesting. And and yeah,
it's it's interesting actually. I
remember giving a I think I gave the it
was the closing keynote at Devops UK.
And I gave I gave a session and and
about, you know, you know, what a future
world will look like with AI-native
development. And they came back they
came up to me at the end of the of the
session and they and they were like they
you know, they had like worry on their
face going, you know, you're you're
projecting a future here where where
developers just don't code. Is that is
that true? And I'm like, well, you know,
honestly, I I think you'll you'll you'll
be hard-pressed to find anyone who will
say at some, you know, code will always
be a thing. And I and I, you know, while
you'll have some skeptics that will say
not in my lifetime, it's it's going to
happen at some point. It's just a level
of abstraction above where we are. The
question is, I think, when. And and I
think, yeah, it depends, I guess,
whether a developer is so attached to
the coding or whether they're attached
to the creation like, you know, the the
the build, the complexity of of the
problem-solving and the creation. And I
always think people who people who care
about the creation, the construction
almost, the the how I build this thing
in terms of how I architect it, how I
think about various things fit, you
know, integrating and building together,
that's all that's going to be there.
And hopefully we'll
Yeah,
hopefully we'll abstract ourselves on
top of that pile still and we can still
make, you know, have input into those
discussions. But I think for people who
are like fully attached to code, that's
that's, in my opinion, certainly and I
think a lot of people's, it's it's
absolutely going to be reduced and and
someday most likely I think pushing the
whole, isn't it? It is. It's a very hard
thing.
>> is definitely becoming less important.
That doesn't mean that the quality of
the output of that artifact doesn't
matter. In fact, all of the best
practices that we followed all these
years are just as important as before.
And, you know, having code that is
linted such that you can actually read
it and maintain it is really important.
And having code that is incredibly
well-structured is really important.
And, you know, the art of selecting what
dependencies that you're using, you
know, don't definitely want to be
picking the latest version version of
Next.js as as recent events have shown
us. But the the the art of like actually
picking what modules, dependencies,
architecture that you're going to use
becomes the part of the craft that
becomes more important in my head. And,
you know, the actual line-by-line
writing and production of code is sort
of the thing that that that becomes
less.
One of the funny things about NearForm
is as a business we've always hired
senior staff. So I think the average
experience in the business runs about 8
years. But last, you know, 10, 15, 20
years of experience.
And it feels like those types of of of
developers are going to have a much more
productive time in steering some of
these tools, right? Like, it's it's
going to be interesting to see over the
next couple of years what that does to
the shape of general software
engineering teams.
One, you know, really unfortunate
artifact we've seen of this AI-native
era is probably the the the the kind of
reduction in hiring pipelines and also
what the
what [clears throat] the future looks
like for junior developers. It's it's
become a bit of a challenging time and,
you know, that that's something that
probably bums me out a little bit. Yeah,
and I guess there's a lot of kind of
like, I mean, the fear, uncertainty, and
doubt here is quite high in terms of
what does this mean for junior
developers?
But I guess kind of like
my opinion almost on this is is
I guess senior developers are more
likely to be able to naturally switch
over because they just have that
experience and they have that underlying
knowledge. I think the path of a junior
developer is just going to be different.
I think they're going to have to learn
different things. And arguably, I could
I could almost say, well, actually,
by being a junior developer, you're
going to be naturally more AI-native
because it's that's the path you learn.
And so we're going to have probably have
this this switch over where
the junior developers are actually going
to be
somewhat more reliant but also more more
happy, more more more
they will choose to use AI probably with
a lower level with a lower bar than more
of a senior developer. So they're
probably jumping into it more.
But that senior developer today
certainly does have that kind of like
more of that knowledge, particularly
around when they're writing specs, what
they want and why they they know why
they want it that way.
Yeah.
>> [snorts]
>> And I'm even not not as worried about
this notion of, you know, all of a
sudden teams just being seniors and the
pipeline of junior talent drying up. I
think the reality of market economics is
that nobody's going to let that happen.
And the need junior team members is
going to be very, you know, very quickly
solved by
you know, hiring pipelines and so on.
That that's going to have to be balanced
at some point in the future. And there
might be a minor reckoning, but we're
still going to need junior developers
that we grow into senior talent. Maybe
that more progressive mindset of
somebody who hasn't been doing this for
as long is more open to the change that
AI-native brings and actually it ends up
being an advantage. Who knows, right?
Yeah. No, I very much agree.
So so we talked a little bit about specs
there as well.
I guess when we think about from the
developer point of view,
the developers are going to be
potentially writing specs, maybe
manually, maybe through agents or or
LLMs.
The the specs ultimately will absolutely
be consumed by agents. Um but we're at
that at funny crossroad where kind of
like both the agent or both an LLM and
and an agent
and a human need to need to read this
and need to understand it and because
one is generating code from it, the
other one is trying to maintain it from
the point of view of
uh you know, making sure the features
are
are correct and well-written, etc.
Who's the who would you say needs to be
the the primary stakeholder? Who's the
person where this specification should
be written for? A person. And I guess a
little bit of a a little bit of a
a comparison here, I guess, is when we
write code today, we have two options.
We either make it, you know, the most
performant, most effective code
possible, which means we're writing for
a for a you know, maybe it's a JDK to or
you know, the machine code that is that
is the most performant, most effective
possible. That makes it far less
maintainable. So, we very often take you
know, make decisions to make something
more maintainable because we feel well,
we're the ones who are trying to
maintain this and read this as well.
Let's make it most readable for us and
then and let the let the compilers and
everything else
deal with a lot of the efficiencies
after the sake. So,
yeah, who is this primary artifact, the
spec,
uh written for
uh you know, primarily?
Yeah, that's an interesting question and
I I like the sort of code optimization
comparison. Um I also love that you have
to get the JDK and there's somewhere
your roots are showing through here,
Simon. That's great.
Yeah, my my JDK my JDK gray hairs, yeah.
Yeah, yeah. Um I think that ultimately,
for me at least, writing the specs for
human consumption is absolutely vital
because that review phase is quite
important. Um if you are writing outputs
purely for the consumption of a model,
um you're probably not really reviewing
what it is that's that's been generated.
You know, if you're generating a PRD off
of a transcript and just blindly
accepting it, in my eyes, you've
probably missed the purpose of spectrum
development in the first place. And
actually, the honing of that spec, you
know, however much some developers may
not enjoy, you know, crafting markdown
is actually the the really important
part of this process.
Um
in terms of like,
you know, the model being able to
interpret what's been written, I
actually don't [clears throat] know how
much of a consideration that's been in
my experience. Um you know, models are
incredibly adaptable, for sure. You
know, if we're putting in like, I don't
know, a PDF of a Gantt chart, we're
probably going to have a bad time.
That's not going to go well.
Um but, you know, things like Mermaid JS
syntax, which I've always done anyway,
or or even just the the subset of web
sequence diagram syntax, that type of
thing
in technical documentation is
invaluable. If you've been If you've
sort of come of age as a developer in
the world of building specifications in
markdown on GitHub, you're going to have
a great time. If you've come of age in
the world of oh, I don't know,
um you know, Microsoft Word documents
and diagrams scaffolded using those
constructs in in in in XML, which is
ultimately what the Word format breaks
down to, probably not going to have as
good of a time.
Um I've found that, you know, the kind
of modern way the developers architect
their their documentation, models are
just really good at reading and that's a
really nice coincidence. Yeah. Yeah, no,
absolutely. And we talked we we kind of
like mentioned there a little bit about
maintenance. I guess um
we're going to have the same issue with
specs, right? How do we make sure that
specifications don't become stale, that
developers are continually upgrading the
the the spec and it doesn't it doesn't,
you know, get out of sync. Um I guess
how when when we think about like BEMAD
specifications, the the BEMAD method,
how do we how do we make sure that this
isn't a turning into a maintenance hell
and that we don't get stale
documentation that just sits there,
nobody reads it, similar to a kind of
like what we saw the PRD become? I think
there's this like continuum, isn't
there? Um in the the world of spectrum
and between spec as source as the kind
of the first term, um you know, the
the spec as the the baseline artifact
that the code is generated off such that
you throw away the spec and get the
exact same code artifact or very similar
code artifact as a result when you
regenerate your code, versus a a more
kind of spec-first um driven methodology
where the specs are essentially, you
know, they last for the lifecycle of the
epic or the feature or the task and then
get thrown away. And so, you know, tied
back to that is this world of
maintaining the documentation. And I
feel like as the frameworks evolve, we
will end up more in a world of spec as
source where the really important
artifact is the spec.
You know, cascading all the way back to
the product requirements document. But
in the in the immediate term, we are
definitely seeing some degree of like
documentation rot and documentation
going out of out of state or out of out
of sync, [clears throat] a little bit
stale.
Um in BEMAD specifically, I've seen this
solved for a little bit through the
ability to inject into the backlog
>> [clears throat]
>> new work items that,
you know, might might alter the course
of development. And within that work log
item in the backlog, you will also have
a specific spec for the story that talks
a little bit about the detailed
implementation of that story and what we
expect from it. Does that cascade back
neatly to the PRD and architecture
document if if needed? Sometimes, but
not always. Um and that just feels like
a a direction of
type documentation will wind up also
being kept in sync. Um feels feels like
that's the way that that that the
tooling is headed, but we're certainly
not there yet. Yeah. It's interesting
when we talk about it cuz there's like,
you know, you talk about tooling there
and that's the way the tooling is
heading. And and I guess there's like
like any major kind of change to it to
our industry, there's there's there's
different things that need to change.
There's tooling, there's practices and
process, there's the human cultural
side.
Um And and like DevOps [clears throat]
is a great example of people sometimes
initially over over-rotating on the
tooling, but actually coming back to
realize actually, this is a this is a
team approach, it's cultural change that
we need to address first. Um I guess
BEMAD, let's let's ask the same question
of BEMAD. Is this fundamentally
um a technological problem or is this a
cultural practice that we need to
change?
I think it's a mixture of both, but it
sort of starts out in the world as a as
a a change in culture. Mhm. Um so, what
what it sort of does is it forces you up
front to expose a lot of the assumptions
that might exist within a software
project.
Um because, you know, as we discussed
earlier, if you if you're unearthing
these discoveries and these assumptions
um as development is ongoing, you know,
results may vary. And so, it's very
important to have a well-aligned
um piece of documentation with all of
the stakeholders that talks about what
exactly it is that you're building. And
to me, that's, you know, a pure cultural
change.
Um There are also kind of technical
practice changes coming about as a
result of the use of many of these STD
tools, BEMAD included.
Um
in particular, probably the the worst
culture technical change that I've seen
is probably the the transition from
teams to sort of the sole contributor.
And that's one of the things we are most
focused in trying to solve for. Um is
how do you scale
um a spec-driven framework to an entire
team of developers rather than a an
individual contributor that is taking on
the role of DevOps plus front-end
engineer plus back-end engineer plus,
you know, the list goes on. I think
that's that's almost, you know, not a
great way to be building within the
enterprise and we need to better solve
for that collaboration piece.
Um and although right now the challenges
are purely technical,
um it feels like ultimately a you know,
it's a cultural it impacts the culture
because, you know, you're expecting an
individual contributor to be able to
wear all these hats.
The the the limitation is purely
technical. It is that right now,
we are mixing, you know, the the work of
the back-end and the front-end engineer
in a decomposed task lists
um
uh that that that are output of of a lot
of these spec-driven tools, assuming
full-stack engineering, but in reality,
we could be aligning these tasks to
individual individual roles and have
people contribute. So, I'm um
I am optimistic of the future for the
sort of more collaborative culture that
spec-driven will will bring. Um but the
the tooling right now just needs to
catch up. Yeah. I love to I love the
phrase you used there as well where it's
it's like I think you
you mentioned forcing function, which I
think, you know, problems with a culture
change in terms of the way we go about
building software or or doing anything
in in the space of tech, you you often
have all the desire you want in trying
to make that change, but ultimately,
it's the tooling which is the forcing
function that encourages and ensures
people are actually taking those steps.
And I think it's the way it's the
tooling that helps train us to make
those cultural kind of steps
to to to ensure we actually follow that.
And over time, yeah, we probably do
we'll probably do that without even
thinking, but it's that transition
whereby the tooling can really help
teams
grow fast. And I think if we I I really
liked what you were talking about with
the collaboration and the teams. And I
guess I'd love to ask a couple of
questions. When First of all, maybe go
into more depth on specs and then I'd
I'd love to kind of like understand at
what point does that does that make it
too heavy weight? So, so why don't we
start with specs? Um
this is a cultural change to actually,
you know, get people to sit down and and
and and write those specifications and
think out what they need to put into
those specifications. I guess at what at
what depth do we need um detail about
every aspect of a project uh whereby
that's going to maybe we overthink
things or it actually starts slowing us
down versus versus helping us. Where's
the where's the right level for for
detail, I guess, in those
specifications?
Yeah, it's it's interesting because I
think in the world of startups, you
know, the the idea of overly verbosely
specifying what it is that you want to
build is, you know, almost sort of a bad
word, right? The super detailed spec can
can slow teams down. Um
I feel like the right size
spec problem is something that is
another challenge with the tooling right
now. We talked earlier a little bit
about rapid prototyping not being a
great fit for vibe coding
bug fixing not being a great fit for a
vibe coding.
Um
And right now it feels like the
the sort of the scale of the specs that
frameworks like BMAT produce can be
quite excessively verbose and heavy.
That's one of the things that we're
looking to try and trim.
Because not only we're looking to
right-size the specs for human context,
right? But we're also limited in how
much the model can can comprehend. And
the quality of outputs will go down the
more and more the context window we take
off with with with just specs, right? Um
so that right-size question is probably
one of the most important things for
these frameworks to get right. Um it
feels to me like BMAT is the closest
approximation of that I've seen to date.
But it's not perfect. It does some
really clever things around very lengthy
documents like PRDs and architecture
documents called sharding.
Which is super clever. So what it will
do is split up a requirements document
such that the functional requirements
per epic are split.
And then a architecture document such
that components are split such as front
end and back end.
And only subsets of those shared
documents are included in the context
window when interacting with the model.
And it's some of the cleverness like
that that makes me think this is like
the best approximation right now of what
spec driven looks like in providing the
best possible honed context to a model.
Yeah.
In theory every line of spec helps the
model and it's really just about
optimizing for context window. But in
reality that can become excessive. So
like it's one of the most important
things I think to optimize for that
length of a spec and you know, how big
can it be before it starts hurting
rather than being helpful.
That's where these frameworks I think
are going to longer term help us. Yeah.
And gosh, this resonates so so much. I'm
literally doing something right now with
a whole bunch of a whole bunch of kind
of like spec style documentation
markdown files
that are kind of like sharing core
security practices and I was practices
and we're talking like 80 different
files of of
best practices and policies of how to
write secure software. Now if we was to
throw all of that directly at a
an LLM and say right do a code review
here,
there's just too much context for it to
kind of like hold in and
say yeah, I'm going to
I'm going to do all of this and I'll do
I'll do it very very carefully. But the
more I'm thinking about it and and the
way I'm trying to the way I'm
approaching this maybe even as a code
review is to perhaps say well, let's
actually let's actually try and target
you know, various flows whereby I'm
sharding is a great way of saying
actually. I'm looking at very specific
areas. Maybe start off with
authentication. Let's let's see let's do
a code review for authentication across
this across this massive app. Because
otherwise you've got so much context and
you've got so much code that you're
trying to look at. It's just it's not
going to go do a good job I don't think.
Really interesting to see is like how
much So right now a lot of the logic for
how this is sharded is said sat in a
framework called BMAT. But if you go up
the chain, right? So like if you look at
the IDE and how it selects the most
relevant piece of context to send to the
foundation model, then you go up the
chain again and you look at the
foundation model as it reasons while
completing a coding task and decides
which bits of context to pull. How much
we can align on, you know, standardized
specs that we're using to to develop.
You know, we have some constructs now
like agents.md.
Um but then we get into, you know, do we
use dot cursor rules or a project
constitution or a
cloud.md. Um
>> [clears throat]
>> Right now it's a little bit of the wild
west. You know, it was nice to see the
MCP get get standard get released into a
an open source foundation. But there's a
lot more to be done on standardizing on
this sort of base building blocks of
specs across model vendors and across
IDEs.
And it's it's sort of exciting to me to
see how much of the sort of techniques
and terminology that we use in the
framework land right now all the way up
here is going to eventually cascade down
into foundation model vendors and also
IDE tool vendors. Um so yeah, you know,
shout out to the the the the vendors of
tools here like let's let's get a bit of
standardization going. The more the
better, right? Absolutely. And I think
that's the key as well because you'll
get you'll get people like using whether
it's IDEs or agents across a company
even wanting the same the same style.
And that agent like the agent agnostic
approach is going to be is going to be
so so important
for for for for this.
So so so you mentioned about
startups. I guess the startup culture of
of really valuing speed and delivery and
experimentation as well.
Is this the wrong approach then for for
a startup or do you feel like there's a
there's a path for where BMAT can be
used there as well? That's a great
question. And like where on the spectrum
does this belong within a startup as
well? Yeah. Um I think the sort of you
know, the world of the the vibe coder is
going to find this very frustrating,
right? Because it's going to slow them
down. And the idea of having gone from
seeing outputs in 20 minutes to an hour
to seeing outputs at the end of a
>> [clears throat]
>> five six hour documentation session will
be inherently frustrating to somebody
who's used to in a in a really low
diligence way just prompting their way
to a really cool application.
Um but for me at least the penny drop
moment was when the quality reflected
the fact that you know, that slight
increase in effort was was put in. And
so you know, when I was able to build
something in let's say you know, two
days of of spec authoring and iterating
through a backlog
that I felt like I understood
as a
and and it felt like an artifact that
would have taken me a month to produce
otherwise
and was probably better code than I
would have written, you know, it's
that's when the the penny really dropped
for me. And a repository with linted
code that had you know, two three 400
unit tests, automation tests,
you know, an architecturally separate
front end and back end, infrastructure
as code like just real wow factor. And I
think that any startup that isn't
leveraging this build methodology
>> [snorts]
>> is going to find it very hard to compete
in a world where you know, the vast
majority of for example Y Combinator
startups are using AI tooling to
a statistic I don't want to misquote but
some you know, incredibly high
percentage of
of startups in Y Combinator are using
tools like this.
It just gives that sort of competitive
edge and the world of building products
just looks so different now because
anybody can show up with a vibe coder
prototype and and show something shiny
to investors. But actually transitioning
it into something that would scale to
the first even 500 or 1,000 users is a
very different question. Um and I I feel
like spec driven is like the the
methodology for doing this. Yeah. And I
think it's it's it's interesting I see
when I see spec driven approaches and I
see kind of more prompt driven
approaches. You almost like start
looking at a prompt driven approach
being a very proto type style where
doing things. I've even known someone to
start with a prompt driven approach and
they send their kind of like code logs
or whatever it is over and say look,
build me a a spec based on these
prompts. You know from my prompts where
my intents are. You can see from the
code that's been generated what has been
built, what I'm happy with. Build a spec
that represents this. And I I guess kind
of like do you feel like that if you
were to like go fully vibe in like
prompts without without building a spec.
Do you feel like that would be a like a
strong limiter for people who actually
wants to go much further, much closer to
production, those who want to scale AI
within their organizations? As you've
probably gathered like that's kind of
the framework of how I think of things
that have purely been prompted. Like
that's not to say that you couldn't
construct a perfect prompt that actually
encapsulates all of the context from
your specs. And just perfectly
right-sizes your context window such
that it's built, you know, task by task
a bunch of different
a
a bunch of different smaller stories in
just you know, very well crafted
prompts. That's definitely possible. But
the methodology of spec driven with the
combination of a framework makes you
more likely to be successful. Yeah.
What's also interesting is like you
know, is spec driven what the future of
AI native engineering looks like? Like
I'm not actually that dogged on the fact
that it is. I'm not completely
convinced. Um it feels as though Cursor
in particular has been slow to adopt a
lot of the primitives and have stayed
gone through the
>> [clears throat]
>> the the recent release with plan mode
feels like a a spec similar to spec
driven or spec driven compatible way of
operation. But it's not exactly that. Um
so like you know, it feels like the best
approximation right now how to work with
these models this this this spec driven
methodology and also the BMAT framework
itself. But that's not to say that you
know, next year that's that's what
things are going to look like. My
if I've learned one thing in the world
of the in the kind of world wind that's
been the last nine months,
it is that my crystal ball is inherently
faulty and I will make terrible
>> [laughter]
>> Who knows? Yeah.
The crystal ball will be I I I saw an
eight ball the other day where it's an
LLM it is an LLM implemented eight ball
which is like oh yeah, everything's
everything's going in the future. So the
crystal ball will be
repeatedly say You're absolutely right.
>> [laughter]
>> So so when we when we think about how
LLMs, you know, typically are are kind
of like better with the the more
structured specs, with with kind of like
clear requirements. When we think about
those specifications or those systems
that are poorly specified, what do they
become? Do they become something which
just, you know, holds technical debt? Or
are they now a liability because because
of the way an LLM is going to is is
essentially going to implement that and
and and make assumptions?
Yeah, it's a an interesting kind of
question, isn't it? Like what becomes of
technical debt? Does, you know, do we
have this new thing that is spec debt or
requirements debt or, you know,
inadequate requirements? Because when
you think about a tech debt, surely
should
at least fade into the background um
because it's now easier to tackle
backlogs of tech debt through agentic
coding, right? You know, the the sort of
drudgery of Well, actually, it doesn't
feel like drudgery sometimes. It's
really rewarding. But but the the art of
like eliminating tech debt is now much
easier to to go after with an agentic
coding system typically. So, you know,
does that become really important um
when you can solve for tech debt much
easier? And in fact, it's actually
something that's not really aligned to
what you wanted to build that becomes a,
you know, the problem. So, like poorly
defined requirements, um does it become
harder after going through, you know,
three, four days worth of of spec-driven
development where you suddenly have this
20, 30,000 line repository? Is it
actually harder to recover from the fact
that you missed some requirements along
the way? And is there flexibility
sufficient in the workflow to be able to
make up for that? Um certainly some of
the techniques I've tried have been
things like injecting new backlog items
to the end of a a backlog to try and
recover and still following the
spec-driven methodology rather than sort
of bailing to vibe coding, which is
definitely a temptation, but following
the the methodology to sort of steer
towards the the desired output. Um but
yeah, it's it's definitely tricky.
Um
the the sort of robustness as well in
that kind of requirements documentation
artifact. Like I know the the Kiro team
are doing loads of really interesting
research at the moment on what makes a
like really good, well-defined,
structured requirements document through
I think the use of like formal methods
um
to to ensure that that that that the
requirements are are um
well-formed and that they complete and
that the gaps are actually identifiable
by the the model as well. Yeah. Yeah.
And and I guess, you know, the goal the
goal here um of of B mad when we think
about agents as they are today,
um
agents are becoming more and more
autonomous.
Uh
are we trying to make them more
autonomous through things like
specifications and through
uh B mad methods because that allows us
to create a a more detailed brain dump
of what we're thinking? Or is it
actually are we still aiming for that
very assisted back-and-forth chat style
flow
uh whereby it just makes it safer
because we're giving it the guardrails
it needs? Is there a Is there a kind of
like a north star that we're we're
trying to get to or both very
applicable?
Yeah, I think it's a bit of both. I need
to get off my fence, don't I?
>> [laughter]
>> If you had to choose one though, Kieran.
I refuse.
>> [laughter]
>> But backlog decomposition for me feels
like the place where there's a little
bit of room now to speed up with the
sort of
um
kind of safety we've injected and
guardrails we've injected into some of
these frameworks. So, like the iteration
of an architecture document and a
requirements document, that feels like a
pretty important stage to still have a
human in the loop. But when you've
decomposed a backlog and reordered it to
your heart's content and you feel like
the the stories that a an agent is going
to go after one by one with a new
context window for each one is in good
shape, I'm not sure that me sitting
there and trusting every single command
that the model suggests I run is
necessarily a great use of my time when
I can, you know, run the agent in a
sandbox and force it between each story
to get commit, get push. And if it
decides to rm -rf / star, that's okay by
me cuz I have everything in Git and it's
in a container and who cares, right? Um
you know, you see all the memes of of
folk vibe coding and seeing it rm -rf
their their entire directory or rm -rf.
Um yeah, the
that becomes less of a problem when
you've got sufficient guardrails and
you're operating in a nice sandbox VM
and so on.
Um
and so it just feels like sat there
iterating through every single story
maybe less useful. I'd love to be able
to accelerate through a bunch of stories
and just review the output of epics
maybe. And so you get towards more of
that autonomy
um when it comes to, you know, as I said
that that earlier phase of actually
writing the specs, authoring the specs,
aligning on the specs, I feel [gasps]
like there's less room for autonomy
right now. Um but but if if we were able
to also make that highly autonomous,
like where do we end up? Are we actually
back to vibe coding somehow? I don't
know.
>> It kind of like relies a lot on trust,
right? Cuz like the if we don't have
trust, we just plain don't have autonomy
because the the the the trust is that
piece in the culture that allows us to
allow the AI agents to to to to stretch
those legs and you know, run run as fast
as Yeah, again, right? It's like having
the
agent enabling you to go after CI/CD and
and then, yeah. Yeah, yeah. So, so So,
does B mad I guess B mad changes that
model then when we think about trust in
terms of it, you know, does it provide
us with more trust and maybe we kind of
like lean a little bit more into
um
I guess quality, the quality of of of AI
output and and how specifications can
you know, can [clears throat] provide
that greater quality because it's
providing those guardrails and as a
result, knowing if those guardrails can
be whether there's automation in the
validation and things like that so that,
you know, things can be raised to us to
say, "No, this is actually
going against the things that we've said
in the spec." We can not just recognize
we know there's high quality here, but
we then have greater trust. Is that Is
that Is that a path where we can, you
know, raise the autonomy bar? Yeah, I
think that that is exactly the lever
that we need to be able to make the
transition in autonomy is you know,
being able to trust the outputs of the
agent. And so, like if in the short term
it looks like, you know, on a per
context window, per story basis we're
reviewing outputs, so be it. But the
more that the sort of quality metric is
pushed further to the right,
um the more that we can afford that
autonomy and the more that we can afford
to accelerate. And so, I think what will
get very interesting is
as we transition um as models are
writing more and more tests to cover
what it is they've done. It's funny, you
know, that the same tricks ring true
like TDD and so on. The the more that
models are able to actually test their
outputs
um and prove that what they claim is
working is is in fact truth um through a
completely separate artifact to it just
interpreting the code, um the more that
we can trust that autonomy. Um and it's
like it's the traditional software
engineering techniques that we've always
used to build trust in a in an artifact
and build trust in the deployment of an
artifact just being used by by agents.
Like I do sometimes wonder is there a a
world where there's some new construct
that that models use to test the
validity of code that we don't
traditionally do in a in a software
development life cycle that can be, you
know, that can be used here. Maybe
that's where the research goes, I don't
know.
Um the the the Kiro folks again,
shout-out to to them have probably done
the most in this space with their
Oh, what do they call them? Checks, I
think. Um but they have a new, you know,
testing methodology that checks for
completeness in a in a way that's not
TDD and is not BDD, but is something
different.
Yeah. And it's funny when we talk about
TDD and like when we think about specs
and I remember in the early days of
Tessel when we were when we were looking
at what goes into a spec and and how
should it be how should it be phrased?
What I what I found like immediately
very interesting was how, well, if you
were to write down a capability in a
specification, you know, you can think
about that in two ways. You can think
about that as this is something I want
the application to do, but also just
slightly written differently, it's it
can be written as a test. You can say
when when this happens, I want you to
provide this back. And that, you know,
it actually turns it into just a slight
rephrasing turns it into actually a
test-driven test-driven development
style approach where actually your
specification is is a list of is a list
of things that you want to be true,
um essentially test cases. So, I guess,
you know, what came first, the chicken
or the egg? What what should come first
in the spec, the the code or rather the
capability or the test?
That requirements writing style, uh
EARS, is that what it's called? EARS
requirements? Um it is setting you up
quite nicely for
a specification of what a test to
subsequently validate that requirement
could be. And so it feels like that is
vastly more important than I don't know,
you know, your your dump from your
brainstorming session earlier on. So,
actually getting a succinct statement of
what that requirement is and being able
to use it as a testable artifact, highly
valuable. Yeah. Um you know, maybe maybe
we'll we'll be in a world where a
Playwright automation test is written to
validate a piece of functionality purely
off of observation of the produced
interface plus that statement with no
insight into the code. The code is a
black box. And the methodology is,
here's the interface, here's the
requirement, prove that this actually
works. Model, off you go. Yeah. And it's
just a LLM as a judge LLM as a judge
style just trying to look at what's been
created.
Yeah, absolutely. And I think actually
there's been there are several papers
that actually show that is a valid that
is a very valid way of of, you know,
running evals and and actually very,
very accurate as well.
Um yeah, cool. I guess what do we wrap
up with kind of like a little bit more
on some of the some of the things that
Nearform have done. Um
I guess you know,
you've run a number of experiments
certainly around Be Mad and SDD and I
think you're from talking with a you
know, a large number of people. I think
you're probably from from a consultancy
point of view definitely the the the the
group that have you know, jumped in
most with this kind of thing. So I'd
love to kind of hear what are what are
some of the most interesting experiments
I guess that that that you have that
you've played around in New Zealand.
Yeah, we've definitely gone hell for
leather.
And so I suppose some of the kind of
challenges that we found in rolling out
a framework like Be Mad to a team of
people since that's how we tend to
operate have forced us to sort of
experiment a little bit with you know,
how we overcome that.
And so I've done a little bit of spiking
on how to codify some of the rules of
our team within Be Mad.
A colleague of mine Luca, shout out to
Luca is doing incredible things at the
moment in forcing the backlog generator
from Be Mad to be able to sync with a an
issue management system like GitHub
issues.
And also being able to orchestrate these
workflows not just locally on a
developer's machine but through
something like a GitHub actions
workflow.
So a super cool way of running
spec-driven development tasks through a
more shared interface where the sort of
work log is visible by all members of
the team through a web browser rather
than an IDE.
Helps with that kind of going parallel
as well. And that's been most of our
experimentation throughout the kind of
latter half of 2025.
And so what we're now toying with as a
business is do we
just you know, embrace chaos and let you
know, a bunch of really clever people
drive their own experiments which yes,
absolutely.
>> [laughter]
>> The open source way. And then 2026 you
know, the hope is that we'll be able to
harvest from a bunch of these really
clever ideas a more kind of unified
Nearform way of delivering at scale
overcoming some of the challenges that
we have with the core framework.
You know, does that one up a module
within Be Mad? Do we roll our own
framework? Do we contribute back to Be
Mad? You know, that very much remains up
for grabs. But it feels like an area
where we're going to need to contribute
something.
Um you know, the hope would be something
in the open source domain
to to try and solve in particular if
we're going parallel across multiple
teams.
That that's been the big area focus.
Yeah. Super interesting. And and to be
honest, I love I love working with you
guys and I I can't say enough nice
things about about you and the team. For
for folks who want to learn more about
or first of all, keep up to date with
you know, some of the great things that
Nearform are doing or you know, reach
out to work with you. What what's the
best ways of of getting in contact and
learning more about Nearform?
Yeah, absolutely. I mean great place to
start nearform.com. The jobs board is up
there. In terms of what we've been
experimenting with spec-driven, I'm the
worst on our blog.
Nothing. I think I've written more on
your blog than I have on my own at the
moment. [laughter]
But
you know, shameless plug come follow me
on LinkedIn. I tend to you know, talk
post fairly techy stuff on the world of
spec-driven development pretty
sporadically.
Our own Nearform insights account on on
LinkedIn also post a bunch of great
content. A couple of my colleagues post
a lot retweeted by the main account in
the world of spec-driven.
And so we're pretty active bunch on
LinkedIn and that tends to be where we
you know, where we talk the most about
our experiments in spec-driven and
what's working and also what's not
working. You know, we're pretty we're
pretty open book when things don't go
well as well. Yeah, yeah. Sounds
amazing. Well, Kieran I think we've got
about two to three hours of content in
somehow around 50 just over 50 minutes.
So we we did well. We did well.
Kieran I think you so much for having me
Simon. Oh, it's been an absolute
pleasure Kieran. I really enjoyed the
conversation and thank you thank you
very much for bringing you know, all of
your and and and Nearform's expertise
and experience to to share with our
listeners. So I appreciate it. Thank you
very much. Absolutely. I'm sure we'll
chat again next time I'm over in London
which I've no doubt will be sometime in
January. Oh, wonderful. We'll see you
there.
Yeah, I hope everyone enjoyed that
episode.
Tell us what you thought and speak to
you soon and see you in the next tune
into the next episode rather. Thank you
very much. Bye for now.